Finding Aid for Ralph B. Baldwin papers, 1949-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ralph B. Baldwin papers 1949-2001
Baldwin, Ralph Belknap, 1912-
8 linear feet.
8811 Aa 2
Grand Rapids, Michigan manufacturing company executive, astronomer. Technical correspondence, 1949-1992, relating to astronomical studies, particularly concerning the moon; correspondence, 1980-1981, used in preparation of his book, "The deadly fuze: a secret weapon of World War II;" speeches on astronomical subjects and pertaining to his interest in product liability reform; and unpublished autobiography.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ralph Baldwin (donor no. 4307 ) first began donating materials to the library in 1965. Periodic additions have been received since then.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Ralph Baldwin, a native of Grand Rapids, Michigan, was a graduate of the University of Michigan. In his career, he has been both a businessman and a respected scientist. For many years he was an officer, later president of the Oliver Machinery Company in Grand Rapids. Outside of his business, Baldwin was a scientist with many interests. During World War II, he was a senior physicist in the Johns Hopkins Applied Physics Laboratory. Here he helped develop the radio proximity fuze described in his book The Deadly Fuze. During this same approximate period, Baldwin formulated the principles of current lunar geology. He described his work in the book The Face of the Moon (1949).
The Baldwin collection consists of general correspondence and technical correspondence relating to astronomical topics and to the publication of his book The Deadly Fuze. There are also speeches, biographical and autobiographical material, and various materials relating to the proximity fuze. The collection largely consists of photocopies of original materials.
Subjects:
Astronomy--United States.; Baldwin, Ralph Belknap, 1912-; Moon.; Products liability.; Proximity fuzes.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Technical correspondence
  - 1949-1989 (primarily on astronomical topics)
    - A-F (Box 1)
    - F-M (Box 2)
    - M-T (Box 3)
    - T-Z (Box 4)
  - 1989-1992 (primarily on astronomical topics)
    - A-Z, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Regarding publication of the book, The Deadly Fuze, mainly 1980-1981 (Box 5)
    - A-Z (Box 5)
- General correspondence
  - 1960s-1980s A-Z (Box 5)
  - 1990s-2001, 4 folders (Box 6)
- Speeches
  - On astronomical subjects, ca. 1951-1990 (Box 6)
  - On product liability, ca. 1951-1990 (Box 7)
- Biographical Material
  - Clippings, reprints, citation (Box 7)
  - Autobiography (unpublished), 1993 and 1998 (Box 7)
  - Oral history interview transcript, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Papers re Crafoord Award, 1990-1991 (Box 7)
- Proximity Fuze
  - Manuscripts of "The Deadly Fuze" (Box 8)
  - Laboratory technical reports on the proximity fuze (Box 8)
Related Material
Ralph B. Baldwin has donated similar collections of his papers to other repositories. These include Grand Valley State University Special Collection and University Archives and the Library of the Applied Physics Laboratory, Laurel, Maryland.